<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.shrmiao.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.shrmiao.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-05T17:30:03+00:00</updated><id>https://www.shrmiao.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Shurui Miao (He/Him/His)</title><entry><title type="html">Zooming in on the Digital Aspects of the Indonesian Elections 2024</title><link href="https://www.shrmiao.com/commentaries/2024/02/09/oii-indo-election.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zooming in on the Digital Aspects of the Indonesian Elections 2024"/><published>2024-02-09T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-09T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.shrmiao.com/commentaries/2024/02/09/oii-indo-election</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.shrmiao.com/commentaries/2024/02/09/oii-indo-election.html"><![CDATA[<p>Written by Rizal Shidiq, Diyi Liu and Justin Yeung</p> <p>Originally published in the <a href="https://www.oii.ox.ac.uk/news-events/zooming-in-on-the-digital-aspects-of-the-indonesian-elections-2024/">Oxford Internet Institute Blog Website</a>.</p> <h3 id="the-context-and-relevance-of-the-2024-indonesian-election">The context and relevance of the 2024 Indonesian election</h3> <p>On Valentine’s Day, 14th February, 2024, Indonesia will hold its fifth direct presidential election since transitioning to democracy in 1998. Over 204 million registered voters across the archipelago will flock to polling stations to cast their votes from over 300,000 candidates vying for over 20,000 national and local legislative seats.</p> <p>Indonesia employs an open-list proportional representation system for its multiparty parliamentary elections, while the presidency is elected by a national first-past-the-post popular vote. With current President Joko Widodo (Jokowi) reaching term limits, recent polls suggest a competitive contest among three candidates (The Economist, 2024). Leading is the incumbent defence minister Prabowo Subianto, running with 36-year-old Gibran Rakabuming Raka, current president Jokowi’s eldest son, in a big tent bid to galvanise establishment backers alongside populists and conservative Muslims. Next is former Jakarta Governor and education minister Anies Baswedan with Muhaimin Iskandar, head of Islam-based National Awakening Party, mainly targeting urban middle class voters. Finally, comes the popular technocratic and former Central Java Governor Ganjar Pranowo, paired with Mahfud MD, current coordinating minister for politics, legal, and security affairs, aiming to gain support from the populous Muslim majority (see The Jakarta Post for detailed candidate profiles).</p> <p>Voters will cast ballots for not only the presidency, but also for seats in the People’s Consultative Assembly and Regional Representative Council that comprise the national legislature, as well as provincial governors and district/municipal legislative bodies. Each ticket represents established political blocs, though most Indonesian parties comprise heterogeneous elements rather than solely ideological bases.</p> <h3 id="digital-media-election-integrity-and-democracy">Digital Media, Election Integrity, and Democracy</h3> <p>The 2024 election represents a critical test for Indonesian democracy as a young, predominantly Muslim nation. Indonesia is classified as a partly free democracy: while the country has held free and fair elections with peaceful transitions of power since the end of the authoritarian regime in 1998, civil liberties can be limited due to e.g. the discrimination of minority groups or the politicised use of blasphemy laws (Freedom House, 2023). For some years, the country has witnessed democratic backsliding through systematic state efforts to weaken opposition groups and concentrate power (Power, 2018). More recently, the political manoeuvring in the high-level Constitutional Court enabled Gibran Rakabuming Raka, the incumbent president’s son, to controversially run for vice president (for Prabowo, Jokowi’s previous-two elections rival), underscoring worries that Indonesian democracy is creeping towards dynastic politics (Paddock and Suhartono, 2024). Adding to these concerns around fair democratic processes are the increasing threats from online spaces – where false information, secretive computational propaganda campaigns and unchecked digital advertising increasingly undermine election integrity.</p> <p>Digital platforms have become fiercely contested spaces integral to the country’s democratic discourse. With over 66% of Indonesians now online as internet penetration expands, digital spaces are poised to shape the 2024 polls even more profoundly than in the past (BPS-Statistics Indonesia, 2023). Nearly half the country’s internet users fall between the key voting ages of 25-46, while tech-savvy millennials and Gen Z comprise over 50% of registered voters. Indonesians really love the internet and social media: they spend 7 hours 42 minutes on the internet daily – out of which 3 hours 18 minutes are on social media (Statista, 2023). While this has enabled more interactive, participatory, and personalised political campaigning, the serious dangers of hate speech, ethnic and religious polarisation and orchestrated viral mis/disinformation become severe. While not a completely new phenomenon since it had been started in the 2012 Jakarta governor election (Sastraamidjaja, Rasidi, &amp; Elsitra, 2022), the growing potential disinformation and political polarisation coming from the buzzers’ activities in the Indonesian political online sphere is alarming, as seen in the 2014 and 2019 elections (Hui, 2020) and recent anti-Rohingya campaigns (Ratcliffe, 2024).</p> <p>On the other hand, higher exposure to social media also means a new way for the candidates to reach voters. In doing so, they reveal the signals about themselves (their identities) and, perhaps inadvertently, their political alliances (their connections). All presidential candidates, and to some extent parliamentary candidates, are very active in social media platforms to woo voters. For example, Anies-Muhaimin, and later on Ganjar-Mahfud, have held a well-attended series of live interactive TikTok forums. A bit of a caveat on social media effects, though: voters still rely on TV as their main sources of information on social and political issues (53 percent). Only 26 percent get the political info from Tiktok and merely 7.2 percent from X (formerly Twitter) (Indikator, 2024. Note: respondents can indicate more than one media source). Thus, online campaigns might not really work for quite a significant number of voters.</p> <p>Not wanting to miss out on the trend, AI is also becoming more popular for the candidates. For example, to soften his image as a former military man and allegedly a human rights abuser, Prabowo camp deliberately uses AI to create his and his running mates’ images into cartoons! Anies and Ganjar camps also launch AI (or digital) platforms – i.e., Haveaniesday.com and https://team.ganjar.ai/. So far, the candidates have used AI for visual image manipulation. Whether they also use it for more sophisticated voter profiling, targeting, and manipulating is still unknown at this point.</p> <h3 id="visions-of-the-presidential-candidates-on-innovation-and-technology">Visions of the Presidential Candidates on Innovation and Technology</h3> <p>Looking beyond social media’s double-edged impacts, the leading presidential candidates have outlined policy visions speaking to Indonesia’s digital transformation and development. Taking the cue from their official (short) vision statement, Prabowo throws the words “digital economy” as part of a national security and resiliency agenda and “technology” as part of a human resource development agenda. Ganjar wants Indonesia to excel in science and “technology” and “digital ecosystem” by prioritising high-speed and affordable “internet”. Of course, the notion of digital and/or technology can be found in the extended versions of all candidates’ proposals and conversations (see Purwanto, 2023 and CNN Indonesia, 2024), but whether they make it into the main vision statement may tell something about the candidates’ priority.</p> <p>All candidates share the same concern on the digital economy, with some variation on its links with small and medium enterprises, creative economy, and infrastructure quality. For instance, Anies and Ganjar also seem to open the possibility to revise the controversial Law on Electronic Information and Transactions (UU ITE), that is oftentimes used to silence the political opposition, disguised as defamation and blasphemy in social media.</p> <p>All being said, beyond the papers and rhetoric, there is no credible signal that the candidates, once in power, would put consequential digital technology reform into action.</p> <h3 id="navigating-the-digital-landscape-multistakeholder-approaches-to-understand-the-2024-election">Navigating the Digital Landscape: Multistakeholder Approaches to Understand the 2024 Election</h3> <p>To champion meaningful reforms and regulations aimed at promoting more accountable, rights-respecting digital governance, stakeholders across various sectors are actively navigating the digital landscapes surrounding the 2024 election. From academic initiatives to governmental frameworks, as well as collaborative efforts with digital platforms, these endeavours collectively contribute to the pursuit of electoral integrity and informed civic participation.</p> <p>In November 2023, the Indonesian General Election Commission (KPU) released the official list of candidates with their short profile or curriculum vitae (CV). In this light, the Leiden Humanities AI and NLP Lab (Leiden HumAN) and the Leiden Institute of Area Studies (LIAS) launched the Political Social Network in Indonesia (POLISONI) project to collect CVs and images of over 300, 000 candidates. Thanks to the publicly accessible digital platform offered by the Election Commission, the project creates a large-scale, multimodal and open-access database of aspiring politicians in the context of Indonesia to allow for studies on Indonesian politics.</p> <p>Preliminary analysis revealed that only roughly 80% of the full profiles are publicly available. In the coming months, the project will utilise this dataset to expand the study of politics in Indonesia beyond national level candidates, but also the provincial and district level political environments. More importantly, with the help of the profile data, it will apply social network analysis to map out how politicians are connected with one another in terms of previous education, employment and familial ties. It will also shed light on how candidates’ self-representation relates to their political positions, religious affiliations and electability through analysis of the text (i.e. platform and slogans) and image data (i.e. profile pictures) in the database.</p> <p>Governmental initiatives like the Election Supervisory Agency’s (Bawaslu) multidimensional Election Vulnerability Index (IKP) now enable granular mapping of socio-political risks to pre-emptively safeguard electoral integrity. Major platforms like Meta and TikTok have also responded by implementing special election designated content moderation policies, yet consistently identifying and addressing trolling and harassment continues to pose challenges. Considering this, Indonesian civil society groups, multilateral organisations, along with Election Management Bodies (EMBs), have been urging technology platforms to embrace greater transparency and accountability in their content moderation policies and practices to protect election integrity. A major development occurred in January 2024 when major platforms signed on to the DAMAI Coalition and UNESCO’s social media for Peace Project joint commitments to fight disinformation, identity discrimination and hate speech, protect children, ensure transparency of political advertising, and guarantee access to platform data for independent research and monitoring.</p> <p>As the official election campaign period concludes on 10th February, the last days ahead of polls will certainly be interesting from a political as well as from an Internet research perspective. After the election, it remains to be seen how the new government follows through on important technology policy rhetoric as leader of the world’s third largest democracy and Southeast Asia’s largest economy. The 2024 race spotlights how the country is balancing the promise and perils of continued digital transformation and an increasingly digital public sphere.</p> <h3 id="references">References</h3> <p>To gain greater perspective on the policies and stakeholders governing online material in Indonesia: https://pr2media.or.id/publikasi/research-paper-regulations-for-moderating-illegal-content-on-social-media-in-indonesia/</p> <p>BPS-Statistics Indonesia. (2023). Telecommunication Statistics Indonesia, 2022. Jakarta: BPS-Statistics Indonesia</p> <p>CNN Indonesia. (2023). ‘Adu Strategi Program Ekonomi Digital Ala Anies, Prabowo dan Ganjar’. Available at: https://www.cnnindonesia.com/ekonomi/20231219153059-532-1039244/adu-strategi-program-ekonomi-digital-ala-anies-prabowo-dan-ganjar. (Accessed: 27 January 2024)</p> <p>Freedom House. (2023a). Indonesia: Freedom in the World 2023 Country Report. Freedom House. https://freedomhouse.org/country/indonesia/freedom-world/2023 (Accessed: 05 February 2024)</p> <p>Freedom House. (2023b). Indonesia: Freedom on the Net 2023 Country Report. Freedom House. https://freedomhouse.org/country/indonesia/freedom-net/2023 (Accessed: 05 February 2024)</p> <p>Indikator. (2024). Efek Elektoral Debat Capres: Perbandingan Temuan Survei Tatap Muka dan Survei Telepon. Available at: https://indikator.co.id/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/RILIS-INDIKATOR-20-JANUARI-2024-1.pdf). (Accessed: 26 January 2024).</p> <p>Hui, J. Y. (2020). Social Media and the 2019 Indonesian Elections. Southeast Asian Affairs, 155-172.</p> <p>Paddock, R.C. and Suhartono, M. (2024). ‘A President’s Son Is in Indonesia’s Election Picture. Is It Democracy or Dynasty’. New York Times, 6 January. Available at: https://www.nytimes.com/2024/01/06/world/asia/indonesia-presidential-election-dynasty.html (Accessed: 26 January 2024).</p> <p>Purwanto, A. (2023). ‘Menakar Arah Transformasi Ekonomi Digital Para Calon Pemimpin’. Kompas, 23 December. Available at https://www.kompas.id/baca/riset/2023/12/23/menakar-arah-transformasi-ekonomi-digital-para-calon-pemimpin (Accessed, 27 January 2024).</p> <p>Ratcliffe, R. (2024). The online hate campaign turning Indonesians against Rohingya refugees. The Guardian, 18 January. Available at: https://www.theguardian.com/world/2024/jan/18/the-online-hate-campaign-turning-indonesians-against-rohingya-refugees</p> <p>Sastramidjaja, Y., Rasidi, P.P., &amp; Elsitra, G.N. (2022). Peddling Secrecy in a Climate of Distrust: Buzzers, Rumours and Implications for Indonesia’s 2024 Elections. Perspective, Singapore: ISEAS Yusof Ishak Institute</p> <p>Statista. (2023). ‘Average daily time spent using various media and devices in Indonesia in 3rd quarter 2022, by activity’. (Accessed: 26 January 2024).</p> <p>The Economist. (2024). Who will be the next president of Indonesia? Available at: https://www.economist.com/interactive/2024-indonesia-election-tracker. (Accessed: 04 February 2024)</p> <p>Thomas P. Power (2018) Jokowi’s Authoritarian Turn and Indonesia’s Democratic Decline, Bulletin of Indonesian Economic Studies, 54:3, 307-338, DOI: 10.1080/00074918.2018.1549918</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="commentaries"/><category term="election"/><category term="indonesia"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On 14th February 2024, Indonesia will hold its fifth direct presidential election since transitioning to democracy in 1998.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Internet For Trust Towards a Multistakeholder Approach in Regulating Digital Platforms</title><link href="https://www.shrmiao.com/commentaries/2023/07/17/oii-internet-for-trust.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Internet For Trust Towards a Multistakeholder Approach in Regulating Digital Platforms"/><published>2023-07-17T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-17T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.shrmiao.com/commentaries/2023/07/17/oii-internet-for-trust</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.shrmiao.com/commentaries/2023/07/17/oii-internet-for-trust.html"><![CDATA[<p>Originally published in the <a href="https://www.oii.ox.ac.uk/news-events/internet-for-trust-towards-a-multistakeholder-approach-in-regulating-digital-platforms/">Oxford Internet Institute Blog Website</a>.</p> <h3 id="regulating-speech-in-the-age-of-digital-platforms">Regulating speech in the age of digital platforms</h3> <p>Digital platforms have become increasingly influential in enabling and constraining information flow in the global public sphere, shaping what we see and how we see the world. Since September 2022, the UNESCO team has been working on developing the <a href="https://unesdoc.unesco.org/ark:/48223/pf0000384031.locale=en">Guidelines for Regulating Digital Platforms</a> under its global mandate that includes the promotion of “the free flow of ideas by word and image”. The aim of the Guidelines is to safeguard freedom of expression, access to information, and other human rights in the context of the development and implementation of digital platform regulatory processes. It argues that such regulatory processes should be led through an open, transparent, multistakeholder, proportional and evidence-based manner.</p> <p>On June 20th, researchers at the Oxford Internet Institute hosted an independent community consultation to stress test the current draft of the UNESCO Guidelines to rigorous examination and evaluation. This community session serves as part of <a href="https://www.unesco.org/en/internet-conference/guidelines-consultation-process">a wider global consultation effort</a> that seeks to ensure opportunities for inclusive participation in the Guidelines drafting-process.</p> <p>The consultation brought together researchers from various stakeholder groups (academia, civil society, government, and the technical community) who covered diverse research interests, ranging from human rights law, online extremism, to deepfake and generative AI, deceptive design, as well as ICT for development (ICT4D). The community also represented invaluable global perspectives including the UK/EEA, the US, Latin America and Asia-Pacific as well as South Africa. Using the Guidelines as a practical anchor point, the session served as a common ground for researchers to engage in meaningful interdisciplinary discussions.</p> <p>The UNESCO Guidelines specifies five key principles that digital platforms should comply with:</p> <ul> <li>Platforms conduct human rights due diligence, evaluating the risks and impact on human rights of their policies and practices as well as defining the mitigation measures.</li> <li>Platforms should adhere to International Human Rights Standards, including in platform design, content moderation and curation.</li> <li>Platforms are transparent, being open about how they operate, with understandable and auditable policies as well as multi-stakeholder-agree metrics for evaluating performance.</li> <li>Platforms make available information and tools for users</li> <li>Platforms are accountable to relevant stakeholders</li> </ul> <p>With these five principles in mind, this blog summarised some of the new considerations that emerged regarding certain aspects in the current Guidelines where there was no consensus during previous consultations.</p> <h3 id="scoping">Scoping</h3> <p>At the centre of the discussion was the key question, ‘What types of digital platforms should be included in the scope of the Guidelines? Or broadly speaking, which level(s) of the digital system, and which aspects of them are we referring to when discussing the issue of content moderation (e.g., risk-based, size and market share, or functionality)?</p> <p>The current Guidelines specifically focuses on user to user services (i.e., any internet service which allows users to generate, upload or share content online) and search services, targeting large platforms, particularly market dominant platforms. The rationale behind the size and market share approach was well acknowledged: platforms in different scales possess different capacity (and incentives in the first place) of investing in content moderation, and digital monopoly should be taken into account when it comes to regulatory frameworks.</p> <p>Most participants agreed that we need to strike a balance between overuse and underuse, ensuring that the regulatory approach is neither overly permissive nor excessively restrictive, so as not to harm human rights or otherwise impede innovation. One way to achieve this balance might be to adopt a tiered and progressive approach that can effectively address different levels of risks associated with different types of online speech. Notably, size and market share varies significantly and are not always correlated. For instance, smaller platforms sometimes create larger abuses as shown in the case of online extremism. As technology becomes more user-facing and reaches a wider audience, it becomes more necessary to assess and address the associated risks.</p> <h2 id="content-management-and-multistakeholderism">Content management and multistakeholderism</h2> <p>The second major question is concerned with content management and the roles different actors play in a localised multi-stakeholder approach. Specifically, how should the Guidelines address the legitimate restrictions of content as enshrined in internal instruments of human rights? What should a localised multistakeholder regulatory approach look like?</p> <p>With respect to a limitation on the right to freedom of expression under the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights (ICCPR), a three-part test is widely used to assess whether such a limitation is justified. The test consists of: (a) the limitation must be provided for by law; (b) it must pursue a legitimate aim; and (c) it must be necessary and proportionate for a legitimate purpose. One concern regarding legitimate restrictions is the varying levels of adaptation and treaty ratification across countries. The issue of legality might also become a slippery slope considering the state efforts for achieving the legality of restriction across the world. Case law plays a crucial role. Citing the <a href="https://globalfreedomofexpression.columbia.edu/cases/new-york-times-co-v-united-states/">Pentagon Papers case</a> as an example, researchers highlighted the potential use of national security as a legitimate purpose that may instead pose threats to speech, particularly targeting journalists and human right defenders.</p> <p>As local governments continue implementing domestic legislation to regulate online speech in the virtual sphere, there is a consensus within the broader content moderation community that a human centred, localised, and multi-stakeholder approach is warranted, which was reflected in community initiatives such as the <a href="https://www.article19.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/A19-SMC.pdf">Social Media Council</a> proposed by civil society organisation Article 19. However, there are remaining questions: How do these initiatives gain legitimacy compared to some existing efforts by government agencies and private platforms (e.g., the Oversight Board)? How can we ensure that private platforms endorse these local regulatory systems, if any?</p> <h3 id="emerging-technology">Emerging technology</h3> <p>In terms of future proofing of the Guidelines, it is crucial to ensure that the guidelines are flexible enough to adapt to new and emerging technologies. There are technical challenges that need to be considered. Firstly, the wide use of algorithmic content moderation may bring biases and varying effectiveness in detecting different types of content, which might disproportionately harm underrepresented communities. Moreover, the rise of generative AI also introduces new issues of content moderation where there might be a potential explosion of harmful content that is generated by AI instead of humans.</p> <p>On a broader scale, the challenge we are facing is the ethical adaptation of any regulatory frameworks in line with ever-changing technology. How can we address the normative gaps between offline human rights principles and the needs and interests of online users? Moving beyond, incorporating risk and impact assessments at the design stage becomes crucial to mitigate potential harms arising from future technologies, especially in the case of AI where our basic understanding is still evolving.</p> <h3 id="gender-and-intersectionality">Gender and intersectionality</h3> <p>While people’s social identities can overlap, which could create compounding experiences of discrimination in the digital sphere, how might we address these different kinds of differences when we aim for a more equitable and inclusive moderation design. Are there specific elements that should be considered to ensure the guidelines are sensitive to gender and intersectionality? A case in point is the moderation of pornography, where important considerations arise regarding gender equality and freedom of expression. Historically, marginalised communities including women have been targets of online hate crimes. While copyright law was previously explored as a means to protect against non-consensual explicit content, the rise of generative AI and synthetic media pose new challenges in applying to combat misuse in sexual abuse cases. From a regulatory perspective, balancing these concerns can be extremely challenging especially in determining what falls under obscenity, or prurient interest. It is also crucial to be mindful of not reinforcing gender roles and stereotypes when applying a gender perspective.</p> <h3 id="the-way-ahead">The Way Ahead</h3> <p>The consultation brought together a large number of researchers working across academia, civil society, government and the technical community. Their representative comments will be included in a new report being compiled by the Innovation for Policy Foundation, that will be shared with the UNESCO team developing the Guidelines. The Guidelines will be finalised in the second half of 2023. We anticipate that our input will help to facilitate future research on digital platforms and online speech governance. Look out for further updates on our social media channels. More details regarding the ongoing consultation process of the Guidelines could be found through <a href="https://www.unesco.org/en/internet-conference/guidelines-consultation-process">UNESCO’s website</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="commentaries"/><category term="internet"/><category term="trust"/><category term="multistakeholder"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recent responses to an independent community consultation on current UNESCO Guidelines for regulating digital platforms.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bridging the Gaps in the Asia-Pacific Information Superhighway</title><link href="https://www.shrmiao.com/commentaries/2019/09/13/the-diplomat.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bridging the Gaps in the Asia-Pacific Information Superhighway"/><published>2019-09-13T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-13T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.shrmiao.com/commentaries/2019/09/13/the-diplomat</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.shrmiao.com/commentaries/2019/09/13/the-diplomat.html"><![CDATA[<p>Originally published in <a href="https://thediplomat.com/2019/09/bridging-the-gaps-in-the-asia-pacific-information-superhighway/">The Diplomat</a>.</p> <p>In remote rural villages in Bangladesh, women in pink and blue uniforms, known as the Info Ladies, arrive on bicycles bringing a connection to villagers who want to see the faces of their loved ones working overseas.</p> <p><a href="https://www.itu.int/en/ITU-D/Statistics/Pages/stat/default.aspx">Among 163 million people in the country, only 24 million are connected to the web</a>. As the world becomes even more interconnected online, there are still many who cannot access the information they need for daily life.</p> <p>Inclusiveness has been a major concern regarding new technologies. <a href="http://uis.unesco.org/sites/default/files/documents/information-communication-technologies-education-asia-ict-integration-e-readiness-schools-2014-en_0.pdf">The 2014 Information and Communication Technology (ICT) education survey</a> by UNESCO showed that only 7 percent of all public schools in Cambodia were connected to a reliable power source, making it difficult to integrate radios and televisions into the curricula, not to mention computers.</p> <p>“Among the ASEAN countries, Cambodia has the lowest literacy rate, which leads to a huge concern, especially when it comes to digital literacy,” said Nou Keosothea, Deputy Secretary-General of the Office of the Council of Ministers, National Committee for Economic and Social Commission for Asia and the Pacific. “They need to work closely to include all, not only for the young people, but also for the old people.”</p> <p>Besides higher rates of internet usage by younger generations compared with older people, pronounced digital gaps are also seen between more-developed and developing countries, urban and rural areas, different income levels, education, and women and men.</p> <p>The internet will be universally available only if these digital divides are addressed, said Misako Ito, Regional Adviser for Communication and Information at UNESCO Bangkok, while presenting UNESCO’s Internet Universality Indicator Framework at <a href="https://www.unescap.org/our-work/ict-disaster-risk-reduction/asia-pacific-information-superhighway">the Third session of the Asia-Pacific Information Superhighway</a> Steering Committee on August 27.</p> <blockquote> <p>“A new standard becomes important today for advocating an internet ecosystem that works for everyone, not only for those who are in power, but also for the end-users, communities, civil societies, and academia,” Ms Ito said.</p> </blockquote> <p>In 2015, UNESCO adopted the concept of Internet Universality, which highlights four key principles underpinning the growth and evolution of the internet, calling for a cyberspace that is based on human rights (R), that is open (O) and accessible to all (A), and nurtured by multi-stakeholder participation (M).</p> <p>To conduct more concrete assessments at the country level, a research framework of indicators was structured around the ROAM principles, with the addition of Cross-Cutting (X) indicators concerning gender perspectives, the needs of children, sustainable development, trust and security, and legal and ethical issues. The framework, collectively known as the ROAM-X indicator Framework, allows governments and other contributors to map national internet ecosystems and figure out possible enhancements both in policy and practice.</p> <blockquote> <p>“I can see a clear framework behind the project implementation,” Nou Keosothea said. “In countries like Cambodia who lack capacities to implement the internet strategies, we need a guideline as a tool to comply with.”</p> </blockquote> <p>As the internet becomes more pervasive, policymakers need to address relevant risks and concerns. For most countries in this region, especially those island countries in the Pacific, internet accessibility is at a beginning stage but growing everywhere, said Kisione Finau, the Director of Information Technology Services (ITS) at the University of the South Pacific in Suva Fiji. “But for internet universality, it’s still a huge task.”</p> <blockquote> <p>“About 15 countries in the Pacific have submarine fiber, with seven countries expecting the construction of submarine cable probably next year,” said Finau. “For most of them, internet connectivity is the highest priority, and the second is cybersecurity.”</p> </blockquote> <p>Cybersecurity relates to the integrity of the network as well as the protection of internet users against fraud and other types of cyberattacks. “Cybercrime becomes prominent in these countries, since the internet might be used as a window to do a lot of illegal activities,” Finau said.</p> <p>Other concerns emerging from the complex internet environment include protection of human rights, cultural diversity and ethical issues, misinformation on social media and child protection.</p> <blockquote> <p>“Age-appropriate is important. Regarding the access to the internet and the information that is harmful to especially kids, we have to be careful,” said Javad Momeni, Director of the Division for UNESCO and International Scientific Cooperation Department of Sustainable Development in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Islamic Republic of Iran. “Other dimensions, including cultural diversity and ethical issues, also need attention.”</p> </blockquote> <p>Following online consultations with more than 2,000 experts and 66 national governments, along with consultative meetings in 32 countries, pilot evaluations were undertaken in Brazil, Senegal and Thailand between July and September 2018.</p> <p>Based on extensive research and interviews with members of the policy-making, regulatory, industry, academic and civil-society sectors, the pilot report in Thailand exemplified how the ROAM-X indicators framework could help countries to gain a holistic diagnosis of national internet policies, digital environments and structural causes of digital inequalities. To this end, the first multi-stakeholder consultation on the national assessment will be held as part of the Open Tech Summit Thailand 2019 on October 1 and 2.</p> <p>With expressions of interest from countries in this region during the Third Session of the AP-IS Steering Committee, discussions are ongoing about the potential of the internet to enable the ROAM principles highlighted in the UNESCO concept of Internet Universality such as human rights, empower individuals and communities, and facilitate sustainable development.</p> <p>Liu Diyi is a master student at the School of Journalism and Communication at Renmin University of China and former intern at UNESCO Bangkok.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="commentaries"/><category term="internet"/><category term="asia-pacific"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How can we foster a more connected and inclusive Asia-Pacific?]]></summary></entry></feed>